- (laughs) He's a little shrimp.
I'm betting that would be 140.
Nothing.
Not a thing.
Okay, so does anybody wanna take a guess
what they would start?
ACE inhibitor, okay.
That's right.
Let's go back to the patient.
42 year old white male.
So you always wanna look at the age first.
Patients that are younger than 75
are gonna be
less than 140 over 90 is their goal.
So you wanna make sure
you know their goal.
If they're older and
they have a co-morbidity,
same goal, less than 140 over 90.
So that's always for the
most part gonna be your goal.
Next thing you wanna look
at is their ethnicity
because JNCA have
different recommendations
for African Americans versus Caucasians.
Now, African Americans, first line.
If they have no other disease states,
this is where some people
get a little bit confused
is gonna be a calcium channel blocker
and we're talking about
the dihydropyridine,
or a thiazide-like diuretic.
ACEs and ARBs are second line.
But if they are diabetic or
have chronic kidney disease
then ACEs or ARBs would
be recommended first line.
Does everybody understand that point
'cause I think people get
confused sometimes with that.
So the next thing you wanna look at,
well, you wanna hope your
patient's not 14 pounds.
Look at past medical history.
So we do have some other
co-morbidities going on.
Dyslipidemia and Type II diabetes.
So Type II diabetes, I
agree with whoever said
ACE or ARB, that would
be my first thought.
You wanna make sure your
patients are on that.
And dyslipidemia doesn't
have a direct response
to what agent you would choose,
but it's just good to know that they have
increased cardiovascular risk.
So vitals, 163 over 95,
definitely elevated,
to their goal of less than 140 over 90.
And then heart rate's always
important to look at too.
If you have a patient
with a heart rate over 100
you might wanna think maybe
they need a beta blocker
if they're consistently having
a really elevated pulse.
Maybe they need some rate control.
Labs, these are just some labs.
You do always wanna take
into consideration potassium.
Somebody said ACE inhibitor.
Do we know what the goal potassium is?
Most hospitals?
3.5 to 5.
So this one's just slightly elevated,
kind of on the border,
not something we would clinically
be worried about the patient having
any real issues.
But you may not want to initiate
an ACE or an ARB in this patient because
their potassium's already elevated.
ACEs and ARBs can increase potassium.
You always want to assess smoking,
drinking, illicit drugs, diet.
And we'll get some of
our cases will have that.
So what's the appropriate therapy?
Well first line in the
JNCA you're going to
automatically have for Caucasian patient
ACE, ARB, calcium channel blocker,
or thiazide-like diuretic.
So that's mostly
hydrochlorothiazide chlorthalidone.
You kind of maybe would
rule out the ACE or the ARB
because of their potassium.
And then you have the
calcium channel blocker
or the HCTZ, either of which
would be a good option.
Usually we start the ACTZ at 12.5
and then we'll titrate from there.
You wanna make sure that
you counsel dizziness,
always hypotension with
the thiazide-like diuretics
as a possibility.
Smaller possibility than beta blockers
but still a possibility.
You're gonna wanna monitor labs
particularly potassium, maybe sodium.
I have seen cases where the
sodium actually goes low.
We remove the HCTZ and it bumped back up.
Counseling points, counsel
on general hypotension.
NSAIDs may interfere.
And then reevaluate in two to four weeks,
that's just gonna be
dependent on clinical use,
so you could say two weeks
would be a fine recommendation,
four weeks would be a fine
recommendation as well.
Does anybody have any
questions on that case
and kind of the thought process behind it?
So now let's say this patient
is an African American male.
Would your recommendations change?
So Berkeley said
take off the ACE and ARB which is correct,
which we weren't gonna
do anyways just because
of the potassium.
But that's the main difference between
Caucasian and African American.
And I wanna stress like I said before
if a patient is African American
and has diabetes or chronic kidney disease
they'll still use an ACE
or an ARB as first line
for renal protection.
Okay, next case.
I'll let you guys read through that
and give you a couple of minutes.
So does anybody wanna take
a stab at this one?
You guys should know
this from case studies
like the back of your hand.
Just nobody wants to talk,
you're in class all morning?
DASH diet, okay.
Berkeley basically said DASH diet,
so look at total fats.
Generally increase fruits
and vegetables, low fat.
Sodium less than 2.3
grams per day ideally.
If they're in that higher risk population
they've actually recommended
less than 1.5 grams daily.
Physical activity try for
about 30 minutes per day,
five days per week which will
get you that 150 minutes.
Alcohol intake, women, limit to one drink,
men limit to two drinks, that's per day.
And then smoking, you
always wanna assess that
each visit if they're willing to stop.
Okay, so next case I'll give
you a minute to read through.
What's the answer to this one?
Lisinopri, yeah.
So, Berkeley already said
you'd change it to an ARB which is exactly
what happens clinically.
They come in and you wanna make sure
that you quantify or not quantify,
determine what type of
cough they're having.
So, it's really gonna
be a hacking dry cough
and a pretty consistent cough.
If they're coming in and
they're having deep chest
coughing up mucus,
that's a different thing.
So you always wanna make
sure that you ask them
to describe their cough.
Again, patient is 71 year
old African American male,
so we're looking at there hypertension.
It looks to be relatively
controlled on the ACE,
so just a switch to an ARB we'd be fine.
Losartan for example you would just start
at 50 milligrams and then
you'd wanna bring them back in
and reassess if their blood pressure's
controlled at that dose.
You might need to go ahead and bump it up.
That was just an example.
Any questions on that one?
If you guys have questions
at all just stop me.
Okay, so this next one.
And what would you guys
wanna do with this one?
George is smiling.
This one's pretty high, right?
2010 over 121.
She's already taken her
blood pressure medicine
so I wanted to emphasize that point.
You always wanna ask have you taken
your blood pressure medicine today.
The answer would still be the
same with what you would do
but then you would also advice the patient
to go ahead and take their blood pressure
medicines for the day as long as it wasn't
too close to their next dose.
And then you recheck it.
You always wanna do a recheck,
make sure the cuff was
sized appropriately.
If there was a manual machine
make sure the manual machine's accurate.
You don't wanna just be
giving somebody medicine
if it was an error on the machine's part.
It's still really high.
So, she's actually over 180 over 120.
So you wanna think about
hypertensive urgency
or hypertensive emergency.
Urgency is not associated with target
organ injury.
And then hypertensive
emergency you are worried about
patients having symptoms.
You're worried about organ injury.
What organs are we mostly
talking about here?
Any heart, brain, right?
So a stroke.
And then you'll have your
peripheral stuff too,
so issues with eyes
and peripheral vascular issues.
Mostly if you're in an outpatient setting
or if you send them to the emergency room,
so if you're in a retail-type setting
you're not gonna be able
to just give them Clonadine
you're gonna have to call.
But what they'll do is
give them Clonadine.
Guideline say 0.2 milligrams
as soon as possible
and then you wanna recheck
their blood pressure,
and then you can give 0.1 milligrams
each hour after that.
In clinic we'll actually
put them in a dark room,
have them lie down,
take the cellphone away type situation,
let them calm down if it's
something that's elevated due to stress.
Alternatively you can use Labetalol,
and the goal is to reduce
mean arterial pressure
within 24 hours.
Also sometimes it's more old school
but you can use Hydralazine
for the same purpose.
Clonadiine is gonna be your most commonly
used medicine and the one
you should know about.
You do have to worry about,
this isn't a medicine that
we use for hypertension
usually around the clock because
it does have really bad
side effects of hypotension
and dizziness, so it's not
good in elderly patients.
So try to avoid it just
for hypertension use,
but in this situation it's okay.
Does anyone have any questions on that?
Okay, we kind of already
talked about this one.
I got a little ahead of myself.
Yeah?
Captopril?
Clonadine.
You could use Labetalol,
you could use Hydralazine,
but any emergency
department that you go to,
it's Clonadine.
Okay, this patient, this
one's a little bit easier
but I just wanted to
bring this up to discuss,
so we'll take a look at it.
What would you guys
wanna do with this one?
Okay, Berkeley said it
increases the Amlodipine,
and that's exactly right.
So I just want it to stress the point that
if they're not titrated to the maximum
therapeutic effective dose--