- Who says yes, they'd change therapy?
Who says no?
The other 50 of you
aren't paying attention.
(laughing)
35 year old female.
What I wanted to stress with this
is can a 35 year old female get pregnant?
Yes, and statins are what?
Category X.
Just something you always
want to think about
if you're in a retail pharmacy
and you see a female that
could potentially be pregnant,
you always just want to make sure
that they're either using contraception
or are at least aware of the fact
that it's pregnancy category X.
It's something doctors
forget to say a lot.
In that case, let's say
she's trying to get pregnant.
What would you recommend?
Okay, lifestyle changes is
a perfectly reasonable ...
Fish oil isn't going to hurt.
Really that's probably it for now.
Mostly, as long as cholesterol,
triglycerides aren't over 500
and cholesterol isn't
in a dangerous level,
then you could just do
therapeutic lifestyle changes
until after the pregnancy
and breastfeeding.
I'll let you guys read through this one.
We have a 38 year old male
who's on simvastatin 20
and gemfibrozil 600 twice a day.
LDL is 110, so just slightly elevated.
HDL is 38
and triglycerides are 240.
AST/ALT normal.
What would you want to do in
this patient at this time?
Barkley's question is if you can take
simvastatin 20 milligrams and gemfibrozil?
The answer is no and that's
the point of this question.
You can, yes.
That's the highest dose you can take,
but ideally you would
just want to discontinue
the simvastatin if the
patient's on gemfibrozil,
pick a more lipophilic statin.
Pravastatin is always a good option.
Less interactions with 3A4.
Of course you want to tell
him to avoid grapefruit juice.
Pravastatin, atorvastatin
is also another fine choice.
It has less interactions,
and if that patient needed that
because pravastatin you
can only increase so high
and only moderate intensity.
If the patient is eventually
going to need a high intensity,
atorvastatin would be a good choice.
The main point here is that you want to
note that interaction.
Also another good option would just be
to switch to fenofibrate, Tricor.
It has some interaction but not as much.
Knowing that interaction
is very important.
Hydrophilic, sorry.
Pravastatin's going to be your best option
but then you have to think about
as high as you can titrate it.
Thank you.
Now we have a 64 year old
female who comes to clinic.
Hypertension, diabetes, and GERD.
On Lisinopril, metformin, and glipizide.
LDL is 178, so pretty high.
Triglycerides, 200
and HDL slightly low at 39.
Her 10 year ASCVD is 7.2.
What would you recommend for this patient?
She's less than 7.5% right now,
something you would definitely
want to continue monitoring.
Moderate intensity was fine.
I think you could also argue
that you would initiate a high intensity,
that she's close and a little bit older
and has comorbidities.
Clinically you could argue
but the black and white per the guidelines
would be that she's less than 7.5.
Then you always want to
reevaluate their lipid panel.
Guidelines say four to 12 weeks.
I usually go with right
around six to eight weeks,
but if your patient also has diabetes,
it's going to make sense
to go ahead and get the A1C
and the lipid panel at the same time,
which might be in that 12 week time frame.
Again, you don't need to
get the LFTs or CPK again
unless clinically indicated.
Now this patient comes
back and has muscle pain
and is feeling fatigued.
What would you recommend?
I heard a few different things
and they're all correct.
There's a few options.
You can stop what medication they're on,
see if the symptoms go
away, and rechallenge.
Alternatively you could lower the dose
and see if symptoms go away.
I have a lot of patients
that are on atorvastatin 80
who will have muscle cramps,
atorvastatin 40 they go away.
Yes, sir?
Two to four weeks.
Wait until the symptoms
resolve, if they resolve.
If they don't resolve, it's
something else going on.
I'd give it two to four weeks
and then you could rechallenge.
Hopefully it's not a disease state
where you're worried about
immediate harm to the patient
so you have that wiggle room.
That's a good question.
You could stop it, decrease the dose,
or you can switch to another statin.
Simvastatin is notorious for
having more muscle cramps
and muscle pains than let's
say atorvastatin or Crestor.
You can always try and
switch to another statin.
There's three good options.
All of them are correct.
I think that's happening in
your guys' case this week
if I understood correctly.
Now this patient's having muscle pains
and tells you they're
having dark colored urine.
What would you recommend
for this patient to do?
Guesses?
This would be rhabdomyolysis, right?
That's what we're worried about.
Dark colored urine,
almost Coca-Cola looking.
What is that from?
It's actually the muscle breakdown,
so it's the protein in the urine
and they need to go
straight to the hospital
is the answer to that.
It's nothing you can do outpatient.
They need to stop the statin first of all
and then go to the hospital.
All they do to treat
rhabdo is fluids mostly
and then monitoring of
course for clearing up.
That's not something that
can be treated outpatient
by just drinking water
and stopping the statin.
It's very serious.
You want to make sure you know to
recommend to go to the hospital.
Okay.
Next we have a 53 year old female
who was started on Niaspan
and she wants to know a little
bit more about this medicine.
What could you tell her
about this medicine?
Anybody?
Okay, extended release would be good.
Why is that ...
Okay, so less to the liver, and what else?
Flushing, yeah.
That's a big counseling
point with this one.
Flushing, itching, red face,
and then you want to
worry about the liver too.
It can also cause hyperglycemia
and hyperuricemia.
You want to take it with
food and avoid spicy foods
and hot beverages.
Flushing might diminish,
and then you can actually
pre-treat about 30 minutes before
with Aspirin or ibuprofen
30 to 60 minutes before,
and that should reduce
some of the flushing.
Now, what do the guidelines
say about niacin use
or Niaspan use?
Okay, so Barkley said
the AIM-HIGH trial said
it doesn't show benefits,
which is correct.
The guidelines actually don't
necessarily recommend it,
but you will still see patients on it.
There are still studies that show
that there is some benefit.
It increases HDL and decreases
triglycerides a little bit.
Mostly benefit is increasing the HDL.
Some physicians will add
it on after statin therapy,
they'll go ahead and add this on.
It's important just to
know how to counsel on it,
main side effects and then
worrying about the liver
and the flushing are going
to be the two main things
you want to take home about this one.
Now we have a 52 year old female
who has a history of hypertriglyceridemia.
She's on Lopid 600 twice a day.
Triglycerides are still
high, even on the max dose.
She wants to take something more natural.
What could you recommend that
would help with triglycerides?
Fish oil, yes.
You have to look at the ...
I can't think of the things right now.
DPA FHA content.
Lovaza, it's already built in for you.
They're going to take one gram.
The over the counter ones,
they might be taking as many
as two pills twice a day,
depending on the content.
It's important over the counter
products, you look at that.
Any omega-3 fatty acids.
The best are going to
be the prescribed ones
because it already has the
correct amount in there.
Now we have a 55 year old female
with five year history of hypertension.
She smokes and doesn't
drink or use illicit drugs.
Total cholesterol is 180.
LDL is 131.
HDL is 35.
Triglycerides, 195.
What would you recommend?
Any guesses?
Moderate intensity, yes.
You would want to calculate,
well I guess that was (mumbling)
You'd want to calculate the ASCVD risk.
Being 55, I maybe should
have made this person
a little bit younger
with no smoking history.
If the ASCVD risk was below the 7.5
and the only other
comorbidity was hypertension,
you might want to try
lifestyle recommendations first
and then go on.
If we're going to tell a
hypercholesterolemia patient
to do lifestyle modifications,
what modifications are we talking about?
The same exercise,
but it's a little bit
different than the DASH diet
when we're talking about cholesterol.
Low fat?
Okay, very good.
Yeah, that's going to be the main focus.
You want to go over what
foods have fats in them.
A lot of people don't
think about the cheese
and the fried foods.
Maybe some of the healthier fats even,
like in cheese, they don't realize.
You want to make sure that
you talk about those with them
and then the same thing,
exercise, lowering alcohol content.
Alcohol's tricky because
it can actually increase
HDL slightly,
but that's still not
something we want to recommend
to our patient.
Just in general, same
lifestyle modifications.
I'll let you read through this.
Now we have a 48 year old male.
Dyslipidemia, hypertension, obesity, DVT.
Doctor wants to initiate Welchol,
which is a bile acid sequestrant.
LDL is high, 160 so it might
be time to add something else
if we can't titrate the atorvastatin.
Triglycerides, 320.
HDL, 42.
Total cholesterol, 199.
Would you guys initiate
Welchol at this time?
Let's say we can't
titrate the atorvastatin.
Yes?