- (mumbling) Most the class.
Nothing.
Okay, so Welchol actually you want to get
baseline lipids because
you can't initiate it
with triglycerides over 300.
So that's why that's important.
For the most part, you're not going to use
a bile acid sequestrant in the treatment
of dyslipidemia in general.
Statins are going to be our first line.
After that we can add on Zetia.
We can add on the new PCSK9 inhibitors,
which I'll talk about in a minute.
Niacin, fish oil, and then I would say
very last line would be
a bile acid sequestrant.
Yes?
Say it one more time, sorry?
Besides the statin?
Fish oil probably.
I mean, dyslipidemia is kind
of easy because it's statins
for the most part.
Welchol can be used and I have used it
in patients that are,
can't tolerate statins,
can't afford Zetia,
then you can use something like this.
It does have LDL benefit.
It's hard to take
and then you can't use it
if triglycerides are high
so it's a more difficult drug to use
but it's kind of there for an option
if all your other options are not,
if you're not able to
use your other options.
So again, don't want to use the face line.
Trigylcerides are over 300.
Discontinue if they get over 400,
because we don't want them to be over 500
and then have to treat
that with another drug.
And the most common one is, well,
Cholestyramine as well, but
Welchol or Cholestyramine
are going to be the most
common ones you see.
Lab values, you guys
already told me these.
It sounds like you know them very well,
so these are just here for you.
Less than 200, and these come
from our ATP3 guidelines.
I think, especially your
class might be the class
that's going to be the
most confused because
they came out with guidelines
while you were in school
and nobody knows how to use them.
Like, providers don't
know how to use them.
Physicians don't know how to use them
because the new guidelines don't even have
cholesterol goals in them.
So what most practitioners
are doing is merging
the ATP3 guidlelines, or the goals,
with the new guidelines, so there's still,
the other guidelines just basically say,
"Start a moderate
intensity statin," the end.
Like, there's no need to reach a goal.
But most practitioners are using these and
I would assume that the
NAPLEX is what they'll test
you on as well and you know those.
And if Capstone tests
you, it'll be on this.
Okay, so in general,
clinical ISDVD patients
need to be initiated on statins.
Patients with an LDL over 190
and that's just with no comorbidities,
if they have diabetes and are 40 to 75,
with an LDL between 70 to 189,
they need to be started,
so basically over 70,
70 to 189, and then the
rest captures the 190.
Also 40 to 75 with an
LDL between 70 to 189
and the 10 year ASCVD risk over 7.5.
So that's when you would start a statin.
Of course, contraindicate in
pregnancy like we talked about.
Anybody with active liver
disease, you're not going
to want to start a statin.
And if they have history of
liver disease, I'd be cautious
to start a statin if
there's another option
that you can use.
If you are going to start
one, that's when it would be
clinically indicated to
check the AST and ALT
more frequently when
you pull a lipid panel
and I do have patients
that have liver disease
that are on statins that do fine on them.
It's just I do check their LFTs.
Lipid panel, again, four to
12 weeks after initiation,
then every three to 12 months.
Usually once they're at
goal on a statin and they're
kind of good, I'll just
bump them to once a year
and make sure that it's
still good once a year.
So high intensity, we have Atorvastatin,
40 to 80, and then the
Crestor, moderate intensity
Simvastatin, 20 to 40,
80 we don't use any more.
And then Atorvastatin,
10 to 20 and low dose
Rosuvastatin and then low intensity,
where there's actually,
there's other ones,
Pravastatin, 80 milligrams is moderate
intensity as well.
Low intensity, there's no real
indication per the guidelines
for low intensity statins.
They either recommend
high intensity or moderate
intensity.
Clinically you might see Pravastatin
or Lovastatin because
they're the cheapest.
They're the cheapest and then Pravastatin,
if there's going to be interactions,
that's the best one to go to.
So you could do Pravastatin,
40 to 80 milligrams as well.
Main side effects, of
course the myopathy's
and myalgia's, elevated
liver enzymes and rabdo,
and we talked about all those things.
So what to do if they're
having myopathy's,
if they're having Rhabdomyolysis.
Hopefully no one has
any questions on that.
Next the fibric acid derivatives, again,
Gemfibrozil has that
interaction with statins,
particularly Simvastatin.
You want to make sure to try
and avoid that if possible.
And Fenofibrate's also another option.
It's a more expensive option,
though, if cost is an issue.
And then you want to make sure that you
same monitoring parameters,
monitor lipid panels.
So I talked a little bit about this,
but I want to talk some more about it,
just so that everybody's clear.
So Zetia is usually an add-on
therapy after you've kind of
maxed out statins or if the
patient cannot tolerate statins.
So statin plus Zetia or Zetia
if they can't tolerate statins
at all.
It has shown benefit, so it
does have a place in therapy.
It's just kind of an add-on
therapy after we've tried that.
PCSK9 inhibitors, did your
class have this in IT?
Or update? Okay.
So pretty new class of drugs,
the monoclonic antibodies.
There's four of them now.
There might have only been
two when you had it in IT,
but there's four now.
I couldn't even tell you
all the names off the top
of my head because they're
new and I don't use them
in practice.
Praluent, they have weird names,
but these are for the
homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia.
That's what they're FDA indicated for.
They also have an indication
if they're on the maximum
statin dose, you can add
one of these on as well.
They're very expensive
agents at this point.
I don't think many
practitioners are utilizing them
frequently unless they have that familial
hypercholesterolemia, but
it is an option and it is
FDA approved, so you should
know about those drugs
and then niacin I think
we covered pretty well
but again, it's going to increase the HDL,
lower the triglycerides.
Aim-High trial said
there's no real benefit.
Other studies kind of differ with that.
It's not in the guidelines
but you might see it used,
so if you do see it used, you
want to think about the liver
function test and the flushing,
so red flushing.
If they do have that, you can
give aspirin or ibuprofen,
30 to 60 minutes ahead of time.
Okay, any questions on that?
So let's take like really
just a five minute break
because there's not much
of the lecture left.
That being said, let's
talk about obesity briefly.
So obesity's very
straightforward, very simple,
but just a refresher on some of the drugs,
when you should use them, et cetera.
So I'll let you read
through that real quick.
So we have a 31 year old male, 194 pounds,
five foot five, doesn't
exercise, eats a lot of fast food
because he's in pharmacy school.
He's noticed some weight
around his abdomen
over the last few months, smokes, drinks.
So, calculate a BMI for him.
Hopefully you guys
remember how to do this.
Does anybody have one?
31.4, anyone get anything different?
I don't know if I, okay.
I have 29, but I could have
typed something in wrong.
So let's go with 29.
So this is just a refresher.
Underweight's going to be less than 18.5.
Normal is 18.5 to 24.9.
Overweight's 25 to 29.9.
Obese starts at 30,
technically, to 34.9 and
then they classify severely
obese as a separate thing,
35 to 39.9 and then anything over 40
is going to be morbidly
obese, and that's when
bariatric surgery can
be considered and we'll
go through that in just a minute.
So let's say their BMI's 29.
That's going to put him as overweight.
So what would you start at this point?
I heard a diet and exercise
and that's accurate.
So pharmacotherapy is not
indicated until their BMI's
over 30 and I'd like to
say that the guidelines,
I think sometimes students get confused.
It's not if you're BMI's over
30 you automatically start
on a pharmacotherapy agent.
Pharmacotherapy agents
for obesity are only going
to decrease you by about
three to six kilograms,
which is approximately
more or less five to 10%
of body weight.
Those should only be
initiated after trying diet
and exercise lifestyle
changes for about six months
with no improvement seen
and then the BMI's over 30
and they have comorbidities,
then you can start
a pharmacotherapy agent,
but it's not something
if you're reading a patient
case or if when you're out
on rotations you see a
patient has a BMI over 30,
we're going to put everybody
in the world on Orlistat
or something like that.
If that was the case,
most people in America
would be walking around on
some type of anti-obesity
medicine, right?
So that's just not the case.
So I want to make sure that that's clear,
that when you do see your Capstone cases,
you're not trying to start
people on that right away.
First line's always, always going to be
lifestyle recommendations.
So, smoking cessation counseling.
Again, exercising at least three
times a week for 30 minutes
ideally five times a week for 30 minutes,
sometimes it's hard to
get patients to start off
exercising five times a
week, 30 minutes a day.
So it's okay to stay,
"Let's start two days a week
"or three days a week" and
then increase from there.
Also that 30 minutes can
be broken up into 10 minute
increments.
They did a study with that,
so if you want to exercise
10 minutes before work,
10 minutes at lunch,
and then 10 minutes after
work, that's you're 30 minutes.
Technically.
So healthy diet, more or
less 1500 kilocals per day.
Three meals per day with two
snacks is the healthiest way
to eat and again, watching your calories,
watching your carbohydrates.
Increase raw foods, fruits
and vegetables are going
to be the healthiest.
The same things that we
talked about with the TLC diet
and the dash diet.
Same principles apply to obesity.
And then increase protein
and decrease fats and
carbohydrates.
So now read through that real quick.
So now he comes back and his BMI's higher.
So now it's 33, which is over
30, like we talked about.
His waist circumference is 42.
Do you know what the cutoff
is we're looking for men
for waist circumference?
40, mm-hmm, so he's over that.
Not eating healthy, not exercising,
and now he has hypertension
and dyslipidemia,
so we have some comorbidities.
What's an appropriate
treatment option at this point?
BELVIQ, okay.
So we could start a pharmacotherapy agent.
Other complications, this should
be pretty straightforward.
I mean, we could have
diabetes, heart issues,
brain issues, kidney issues, liver issues,
a lot of things come along with obesity.
And is bariatric surgery
an option at this point?
No.
Only over 40 and that still
has to be heavily considered
if they have a lot of
comorbidities, high cardiovascular
risk, and then it's a complicated process.
They have to decrease the
amount of food they eat
ahead of time and afterwards,
so really that's reserved
for very