- (laughs) He's a little shrimp.
I'm betting that would be 140.
Nothing.
Not a thing.
Okay, so does anybody wanna take a guess
what they would start?
ACE inhibitor, okay.
That's right.
Let's go back to the patient.
42 year old white male.
So you always wanna look at the age first.
Patients that are younger than 75
are gonna be
less than 140 over 90 is their goal.
So you wanna make sure
you know their goal.
If they're older and
they have a co-morbidity,
same goal, less than 140 over 90.
So that's always for the
most part gonna be your goal.
Next thing you wanna look
at is their ethnicity
because JNCA have
different recommendations
for African Americans versus Caucasians.
Now, African Americans, first line.
If they have no other disease states,
this is where some people
get a little bit confused
is gonna be a calcium channel blocker
and we're talking about
the dihydropyridine,
or a thiazide-like diuretic.
ACEs and ARBs are second line.
But if they are diabetic or
have chronic kidney disease
then ACEs or ARBs would
be recommended first line.
Does everybody understand that point
'cause I think people get
confused sometimes with that.
So the next thing you wanna look at,
well, you wanna hope your
patient's not 14 pounds.
Look at past medical history.
So we do have some other
co-morbidities going on.
Dyslipidemia and Type II diabetes.
So Type II diabetes, I
agree with whoever said
ACE or ARB, that would
be my first thought.
You wanna make sure your
patients are on that.
And dyslipidemia doesn't
have a direct response
to what agent you would choose,
but it's just good to know that they have
increased cardiovascular risk.
So vitals, 163 over 95,
definitely elevated,
to their goal of less than 140 over 90.
And then heart rate's always
important to look at too.
If you have a patient
with a heart rate over 100
you might wanna think maybe
they need a beta blocker
if they're consistently having
a really elevated pulse.
Maybe they need some rate control.
Labs, these are just some labs.
You do always wanna take
into consideration potassium.
Somebody said ACE inhibitor.
Do we know what the goal potassium is?
Most hospitals?
3.5 to 5.
So this one's just slightly elevated,
kind of on the border,
not something we would clinically
be worried about the patient having
any real issues.
But you may not want to initiate
an ACE or an ARB in this patient because
their potassium's already elevated.
ACEs and ARBs can increase potassium.
You always want to assess smoking,
drinking, illicit drugs, diet.
And we'll get some of
our cases will have that.
So what's the appropriate therapy?
Well first line in the
JNCA you're going to
automatically have for Caucasian patient
ACE, ARB, calcium channel blocker,
or thiazide-like diuretic.
So that's mostly
hydrochlorothiazide chlorthalidone.
You kind of maybe would
rule out the ACE or the ARB
because of their potassium.
And then you have the
calcium channel blocker
or the HCTZ, either of which
would be a good option.
Usually we start the ACTZ at 12.5
and then we'll titrate from there.
You wanna make sure that
you counsel dizziness,
always hypotension with
the thiazide-like diuretics
as a possibility.
Smaller possibility than beta blockers
but still a possibility.
You're gonna wanna monitor labs
particularly potassium, maybe sodium.
I have seen cases where the
sodium actually goes low.
We remove the HCTZ and it bumped back up.
Counseling points, counsel
on general hypotension.
NSAIDs may interfere.
And then reevaluate in two to four weeks,
that's just gonna be
dependent on clinical use,
so you could say two weeks
would be a fine recommendation,
four weeks would be a fine
recommendation as well.
Does anybody have any
questions on that case
and kind of the thought process behind it?
So now let's say this patient
is an African American male.
Would your recommendations change?
So Berkeley said
take off the ACE and ARB which is correct,
which we weren't gonna
do anyways just because
of the potassium.
But that's the main difference between
Caucasian and African American.
And I wanna stress like I said before
if a patient is African American
and has diabetes or chronic kidney disease
they'll still use an ACE
or an ARB as first line
for renal protection.
Okay, next case.
I'll let you guys read through that
and give you a couple of minutes.
So does anybody wanna take
a stab at this one?
You guys should know
this from case studies
like the back of your hand.
Just nobody wants to talk,
you're in class all morning?
DASH diet, okay.
Berkeley basically said DASH diet,
so look at total fats.
Generally increase fruits
and vegetables, low fat.
Sodium less than 2.3
grams per day ideally.
If they're in that higher risk population
they've actually recommended
less than 1.5 grams daily.
Physical activity try for
about 30 minutes per day,
five days per week which will
get you that 150 minutes.
Alcohol intake, women, limit to one drink,
men limit to two drinks, that's per day.
And then smoking, you
always wanna assess that
each visit if they're willing to stop.
Okay, so next case I'll give
you a minute to read through.
What's the answer to this one?
Lisinopri, yeah.
So, Berkeley already said
you'd change it to an ARB which is exactly
what happens clinically.
They come in and you wanna make sure
that you quantify or not quantify,
determine what type of
cough they're having.
So, it's really gonna
be a hacking dry cough
and a pretty consistent cough.
If they're coming in and
they're having deep chest
coughing up mucus,
that's a different thing.
So you always wanna make
sure that you ask them
to describe their cough.
Again, patient is 71 year
old African American male,
so we're looking at there hypertension.
It looks to be relatively
controlled on the ACE,
so just a switch to an ARB we'd be fine.
Losartan for example you would just start
at 50 milligrams and then
you'd wanna bring them back in
and reassess if their blood pressure's
controlled at that dose.
You might need to go ahead and bump it up.
That was just an example.
Any questions on that one?
If you guys have questions
at all just stop me.
Okay, so this next one.
And what would you guys
wanna do with this one?
George is smiling.
This one's pretty high, right?
2010 over 121.
She's already taken her
blood pressure medicine
so I wanted to emphasize that point.
You always wanna ask have you taken
your blood pressure medicine today.
The answer would still be the
same with what you would do
but then you would also advice the patient
to go ahead and take their blood pressure
medicines for the day as long as it wasn't
too close to their next dose.
And then you recheck it.
You always wanna do a recheck,
make sure the cuff was
sized appropriately.
If there was a manual machine
make sure the manual machine's accurate.
You don't wanna just be
giving somebody medicine
if it was an error on the machine's part.
It's still really high.
So, she's actually over 180 over 120.
So you wanna think about
hypertensive urgency
or hypertensive emergency.
Urgency is not associated with target
organ injury.
And then hypertensive
emergency you are worried about
patients having symptoms.
You're worried about organ injury.
What organs are we mostly
talking about here?
Any heart, brain, right?
So a stroke.
And then you'll have your
peripheral stuff too,
so issues with eyes
and peripheral vascular issues.
Mostly if you're in an outpatient setting
or if you send them to the emergency room,
so if you're in a retail-type setting
you're not gonna be able
to just give them Clonadine
you're gonna have to call.
But what they'll do is
give them Clonadine.
Guideline say 0.2 milligrams
as soon as possible
and then you wanna recheck
their blood pressure,
and then you can give 0.1 milligrams
each hour after that.
In clinic we'll actually
put them in a dark room,
have them lie down,
take the cellphone away type situation,
let them calm down if it's
something that's elevated due to stress.
Alternatively you can use Labetalol,
and the goal is to reduce
mean arterial pressure
within 24 hours.
Also sometimes it's more old school
but you can use Hydralazine
for the same purpose.
Clonadiine is gonna be your most commonly
used medicine and the one
you should know about.
You do have to worry about,
this isn't a medicine that
we use for hypertension
usually around the clock because
it does have really bad
side effects of hypotension
and dizziness, so it's not
good in elderly patients.
So try to avoid it just
for hypertension use,
but in this situation it's okay.
Does anyone have any questions on that?
Okay, we kind of already
talked about this one.
I got a little ahead of myself.
Yeah?
Captopril?
Clonadine.
You could use Labetalol,
you could use Hydralazine,
but any emergency
department that you go to,
it's Clonadine.
Okay, this patient, this
one's a little bit easier
but I just wanted to
bring this up to discuss,
so we'll take a look at it.
What would you guys
wanna do with this one?
Okay, Berkeley said it
increases the Amlodipine,
and that's exactly right.
So I just want it to stress the point that
if they're not titrated to the maximum
therapeutic effective dose--
- That's the first thing you wanna do
before you add a third agent in this case.
Because he's already on lisinopril 40.
So from 40 to 80 you're not gonna see
too much of a clinical change.
So 40's kinda max therapeutic dose.
Amlodipine we can go all the way up to 10,
and he was only on 2.5,
and his blood pressure wasn't that high
that we were worried about
any hypertensive urgency
or emergency.
So that's a perfectly fine answer.
And then if he comes back
and it's still elevated,
I would titrate again.
So once he was on amlodapine 10
and lisinopril 40, and
it was still elevated,
what would you guys do?
So we'll go back to him.
I think I heard thiazide diuretic.
Yeah, okay, and that's right.
So you always wanna go back and think
what the guidelines say are
gonna be our first line agent.
And he's already on an ACE,
so it's ACE or ARB,
you don't want somebody
on an ACE and an ARB.
So he's already on that ACE,
already on the calcium channel blocker,
then you would just do a
thiazide-like diuretic.
And you can HCTZ, or chlorthalidone.
They're both proven. Yes, sir.
Yeah, I don't know why that's on there.
I don't know why the
calcium level's on there.
Don't worry about that for this case,
but yeah, you would wanna look at that.
Okay, so now this same patient
is having swelling in his legs,
and you examine him,
and he is having +1
pitting peripheral edema.
So why do you think that would be?
Okay, so Barclay thinks it's from
the calcium channel blocker, and I agree.
And you may see that
when you initiate a
calcium channel blocker,
or when you increase dose with
a calcium channel blocker.
What main side effects are we
worried about besides cough
with ACE inhibitors?
Edema, yep.
So, same thing, just in the lips usually.
Lips, tongue, face.
What about a main side effect
with our thiazide-like diuretics?
We kinda talked about that.
Hypercalcemia, and then the hypokalemia.
So really, electrolytes we wanna monitor.
And then what other side effects
do we wanna counsel on
with the thiazide-like diuretics?
Urination, okay.
So yeah, you always wanna tell them
to take it in the morning,
you may have increased urinary frequency.
So now we have a 50-year-old male
who has hypertension.
He has a past medical history of MI.
So what medication would somebody
that has had a past medical history of MI
need to be on?
A beta blocker.
So I think sometimes people
get confused with that too.
No, beta blockers are not
first line for hypertension
per JNC 8 guidelines.
But if you have a patient
that's had heart failure
or previous MI,
you're going to want them
to be on a beta blocker.
And that beta blocker
will serve two purposes.
It will help them with
their other problem,
and it will lower their blood pressure.
So that's a good thing.
So that's the one time that
the rule doesn't apply,
that it's not first line for hypertension.
Now the physician has decided,
okay they're on a beta blocker,
and they're on an ACE inhibitor,
I wanna add a diuretic.
And we know the sodium's
141, so that's fine,
potassium's 3.7, fine.
Creatinine clearance is
just a little bit low, 47.4.
So what diuretic would you think to add?
Chlorthalidone, okay.
That's a fine choice.
So if you look at the diuretics,
you don't wanna use HCTZ
when they get below 30,
but our patient's above 30 right now.
What other diuretics
are options in general
in hypertension, or for
treatment of other things?
What diuretics do we have?
Okay, so we have loop
diuretics, so furosemide.
I just wanna make it clear that usually
you're not going to use
furosemide to treat hypertension,
as the treatment of hypertension.
So they'll be put on it
for peripheral edema,
potentially from heart failure,
and then they might be on it PRN.
It will help with
lowering of blood pressure
if they're on it for something else,
but you wanna make sure
that you understand
that you don't put them on
it as a first line agent
for hypertension.
What else? What other diuretics?
Okay, potassium-sparing,
so we have spironolactone and eplerenone.
When would you use
those with hypertension?
Okay, so if they've had heart failure
it's a good option.
Also if they're resistant hypertension.
So if they're kind of on everything
that's first line already,
sometimes they're gonna have elevated ADH,
so aldosterone, and that's
a good option for them.
What are we worried about with
those potassium-sparing diuretics?
Okay, so potassium too
high, that's a good point.
So you always wanna make sure
you check their potassium
before you start them,
and then about a month
after you start them.
Same thing with ACEs and ARBs,
but this is even more so.
And what about main side effects?
Gynecomastia, yep.
Eplerenone has less gynecomastia
than spirinolactone.
So if your patient's
insurance is gonna cover it,
usually that's a little
bit better of an option.
Again, not first line in hypertension,
but if it's treatment
resistant, you can use it.
There's also triamterene you might see,
not first line,
but especially some of the
more old school doctors
will put them on triamterene, HCTZ.
And then I put this question in,
is MJ adequately beta blocked?
So let's take a look at the pulse here,
what do you guys think?
How do you tell if somebody's
adequately beta blocked?
Okay, I'm hearing 60-80 normal limits.
Any other guesses?
Usually about 60 to 70
is gonna mean that they're kind of
maximally adequately beta blocked.
60 to 80, I would agree with as well
if it's kind of on the
lower end of normal,
all the way down to 60.
Anything below 60
you're gonna kinda start
to worry a little bit,
but that's how you tell.
So if a patient, even if they're on
maximum dose atenolol,
maximum dose metoprolol,
if their pulse is still over 90
that means that beta blocker
is not adequately
working for that patient.
So you always wanna take
a look at that as well.
Okay, these I just put for your benefit,
I'm not reading through these.
Basically goal is gonna
be less than 140/90
as we've stated,
for the most part, for most diseases.
And then you have to go to
the individual guidelines
for each disease state.
So CKD guidelines for CKD,
which is actually now in
conjunction with the 140/90.
But it used to be different.
Diabetes used to be different,
now they're all kinda
getting on board together,
so that's good.
Then I just put in some basic slides,
I'm not redoing your IT slides,
you guys have already
had hypertension and IT.
But main medications used,
main side effects,
so our ACEs and our ARBs,
of course we wanna look out for cough,
and then elevated potassium.
And the edema like we talked about.
Calcium channel blockers,
when would you use a non-dihydropyridine
calcium channel blocker for hypertension?
Or would you use the non-dihydropyridine?
Not too sure?
Maybe some people are
sure, but I can't hear you.
The main difference is gonna be
that these act centrally, right,
they're gonna act on the heart.
So if it's an afib patient
that's trying to be rate-controlled,
hopefully you guys know,
I think you guys had
an afib case last week,
that these are gonna be your
calcium channel blockers
that you're going to.
If your patient also has hypertension,
that's when you would use that medication.
And then your dihyrdopyridines
are gonna act more peripherally
to vasodilate, and then reduce
your blood pressure that way.
So these are gonna be
when we're talking about
first line hypertension medicines,
and we say calcium channel blockers,
these are the medicines
that we're talking about.
Not so much these unless there's another
comorphic condition that indicates
that you would use
verapamil and diltiazem.
Beta blockers, again,
you wanna make sure
that your patient has another indication.
It wouldn't be your first choice to start
unless they're having
repeatedly high pulse
for unknown reason.
And in that case you
would definitely wanna
go ahead an get an EKG
to make sure something
else isn't going on.
But previous MI, or CHF,
that's when you would use these,
and you want to make
sure that you start low
and go slow.
That's how I learned beta blockers.
So start at a low dose and then titrate.
And same thing when you
discontinue beta blockers.
So you don't just wanna
stop a beta blocker,
you wanna decrease the dose
and titrate back down until
you stop the beta blocker.
Then once you have titrated down,
then you can start your new agent
if the purpose of titrating
is that you're switching agents.
You also wanna make sure,
because a lot of our hypertension patients
may also have diabetes,
so if they are on a beta blocker
it's important to tell them that
it might mask the signs and symptoms
of hypoglycemia.
All of them besides, what?
What won't a beta blocker mask?
Sweating.
So it'll mask the palpitations,
dizziness feeling,
but they'll still have the sweating
if they have the sweating.
Okay, that kind of does that.
So any major questions on hypertension?
I tried to kinda cover
through different cases.
Nope, okay.
Well, hopefully that helps to distinguish
a little bit in your head.
So now let's go on to dyslipidemia.
Let you guys read through that.
So we have a 45-year-old
Caucasian male who has type 2 diabetes.
And blood pressure's 135/86,
so just a little bit elevated.
Total cholesterol is 210.
What's our goal here?
200.
HDL is 37. What's our goal for men?
Over 40. And women?
50.
LDL is 170. What's our goal here?
100, so he's a diabetic patient.
And then it's controversial,
but the guidelines actually say
cardiovascular issues as well,
you can push to less than 70.
Triglycerides are 320,
what's our goal here?
Less than 150.
At what point do we worry
about triglycerides?
500, good.
Man, you guys are good today.
And A1C's just a little bit high at 7.2.
Overweight, 210 at 5'6.
Smokes two packs a day,
and somebody calculated their
ASCVD 10 year risk score
at 8.5%.
So what medicine would you want to start?
High-intensity statin, okay.
And which statins are those?
Atorvastatin, rosuvastatin, yep.
Lipitor and Crestor, okay.
And certain doses, so Crestor either dose,
but then atorvastatin is
gonna be the 40 to 80.
20 is actually a moderate intensity.
There we go.
So you wanna look at the age, 40 to 75,
diabetes, ASCVD risk,
and then you'll start a statin.
What labs do you wanna get
when you start a statin?
I heard CPK. What else?
I heard ALT. Let's go with both.
Liver function test, so AST, ALT.
And then you would ideally have
a lipid panel as well.
But CPK, and then your LFTs.
Now, you only monitor your CPK, LFTs
when clinically indicated.
So if your patient is having
signs or symptoms, or issues.
It's not something you're gonna get
every time you get a lipid panel.
So now this patient's
a 35-year-old female.
Would your choice of therapy be different,
and if yes, what would it be?
- Who says yes, they'd change therapy?
Who says no?
The other 50 of you
aren't paying attention.
(laughing)
35 year old female.
What I wanted to stress with this
is can a 35 year old female get pregnant?
Yes, and statins are what?
Category X.
Just something you always
want to think about
if you're in a retail pharmacy
and you see a female that
could potentially be pregnant,
you always just want to make sure
that they're either using contraception
or are at least aware of the fact
that it's pregnancy category X.
It's something doctors
forget to say a lot.
In that case, let's say
she's trying to get pregnant.
What would you recommend?
Okay, lifestyle changes is
a perfectly reasonable ...
Fish oil isn't going to hurt.
Really that's probably it for now.
Mostly, as long as cholesterol,
triglycerides aren't over 500
and cholesterol isn't
in a dangerous level,
then you could just do
therapeutic lifestyle changes
until after the pregnancy
and breastfeeding.
I'll let you guys read through this one.
We have a 38 year old male
who's on simvastatin 20
and gemfibrozil 600 twice a day.
LDL is 110, so just slightly elevated.
HDL is 38
and triglycerides are 240.
AST/ALT normal.
What would you want to do in
this patient at this time?
Barkley's question is if you can take
simvastatin 20 milligrams and gemfibrozil?
The answer is no and that's
the point of this question.
You can, yes.
That's the highest dose you can take,
but ideally you would
just want to discontinue
the simvastatin if the
patient's on gemfibrozil,
pick a more lipophilic statin.
Pravastatin is always a good option.
Less interactions with 3A4.
Of course you want to tell
him to avoid grapefruit juice.
Pravastatin, atorvastatin
is also another fine choice.
It has less interactions,
and if that patient needed that
because pravastatin you
can only increase so high
and only moderate intensity.
If the patient is eventually
going to need a high intensity,
atorvastatin would be a good choice.
The main point here is that you want to
note that interaction.
Also another good option would just be
to switch to fenofibrate, Tricor.
It has some interaction but not as much.
Knowing that interaction
is very important.
Hydrophilic, sorry.
Pravastatin's going to be your best option
but then you have to think about
as high as you can titrate it.
Thank you.
Now we have a 64 year old
female who comes to clinic.
Hypertension, diabetes, and GERD.
On Lisinopril, metformin, and glipizide.
LDL is 178, so pretty high.
Triglycerides, 200
and HDL slightly low at 39.
Her 10 year ASCVD is 7.2.
What would you recommend for this patient?
She's less than 7.5% right now,
something you would definitely
want to continue monitoring.
Moderate intensity was fine.
I think you could also argue
that you would initiate a high intensity,
that she's close and a little bit older
and has comorbidities.
Clinically you could argue
but the black and white per the guidelines
would be that she's less than 7.5.
Then you always want to
reevaluate their lipid panel.
Guidelines say four to 12 weeks.
I usually go with right
around six to eight weeks,
but if your patient also has diabetes,
it's going to make sense
to go ahead and get the A1C
and the lipid panel at the same time,
which might be in that 12 week time frame.
Again, you don't need to
get the LFTs or CPK again
unless clinically indicated.
Now this patient comes
back and has muscle pain
and is feeling fatigued.
What would you recommend?
I heard a few different things
and they're all correct.
There's a few options.
You can stop what medication they're on,
see if the symptoms go
away, and rechallenge.
Alternatively you could lower the dose
and see if symptoms go away.
I have a lot of patients
that are on atorvastatin 80
who will have muscle cramps,
atorvastatin 40 they go away.
Yes, sir?
Two to four weeks.
Wait until the symptoms
resolve, if they resolve.
If they don't resolve, it's
something else going on.
I'd give it two to four weeks
and then you could rechallenge.
Hopefully it's not a disease state
where you're worried about
immediate harm to the patient
so you have that wiggle room.
That's a good question.
You could stop it, decrease the dose,
or you can switch to another statin.
Simvastatin is notorious for
having more muscle cramps
and muscle pains than let's
say atorvastatin or Crestor.
You can always try and
switch to another statin.
There's three good options.
All of them are correct.
I think that's happening in
your guys' case this week
if I understood correctly.
Now this patient's having muscle pains
and tells you they're
having dark colored urine.
What would you recommend
for this patient to do?
Guesses?
This would be rhabdomyolysis, right?
That's what we're worried about.
Dark colored urine,
almost Coca-Cola looking.
What is that from?
It's actually the muscle breakdown,
so it's the protein in the urine
and they need to go
straight to the hospital
is the answer to that.
It's nothing you can do outpatient.
They need to stop the statin first of all
and then go to the hospital.
All they do to treat
rhabdo is fluids mostly
and then monitoring of
course for clearing up.
That's not something that
can be treated outpatient
by just drinking water
and stopping the statin.
It's very serious.
You want to make sure you know to
recommend to go to the hospital.
Okay.
Next we have a 53 year old female
who was started on Niaspan
and she wants to know a little
bit more about this medicine.
What could you tell her
about this medicine?
Anybody?
Okay, extended release would be good.
Why is that ...
Okay, so less to the liver, and what else?
Flushing, yeah.
That's a big counseling
point with this one.
Flushing, itching, red face,
and then you want to
worry about the liver too.
It can also cause hyperglycemia
and hyperuricemia.
You want to take it with
food and avoid spicy foods
and hot beverages.
Flushing might diminish,
and then you can actually
pre-treat about 30 minutes before
with Aspirin or ibuprofen
30 to 60 minutes before,
and that should reduce
some of the flushing.
Now, what do the guidelines
say about niacin use
or Niaspan use?
Okay, so Barkley said
the AIM-HIGH trial said
it doesn't show benefits,
which is correct.
The guidelines actually don't
necessarily recommend it,
but you will still see patients on it.
There are still studies that show
that there is some benefit.
It increases HDL and decreases
triglycerides a little bit.
Mostly benefit is increasing the HDL.
Some physicians will add
it on after statin therapy,
they'll go ahead and add this on.
It's important just to
know how to counsel on it,
main side effects and then
worrying about the liver
and the flushing are going
to be the two main things
you want to take home about this one.
Now we have a 52 year old female
who has a history of hypertriglyceridemia.
She's on Lopid 600 twice a day.
Triglycerides are still
high, even on the max dose.
She wants to take something more natural.
What could you recommend that
would help with triglycerides?
Fish oil, yes.
You have to look at the ...
I can't think of the things right now.
DPA FHA content.
Lovaza, it's already built in for you.
They're going to take one gram.
The over the counter ones,
they might be taking as many
as two pills twice a day,
depending on the content.
It's important over the counter
products, you look at that.
Any omega-3 fatty acids.
The best are going to
be the prescribed ones
because it already has the
correct amount in there.
Now we have a 55 year old female
with five year history of hypertension.
She smokes and doesn't
drink or use illicit drugs.
Total cholesterol is 180.
LDL is 131.
HDL is 35.
Triglycerides, 195.
What would you recommend?
Any guesses?
Moderate intensity, yes.
You would want to calculate,
well I guess that was (mumbling)
You'd want to calculate the ASCVD risk.
Being 55, I maybe should
have made this person
a little bit younger
with no smoking history.
If the ASCVD risk was below the 7.5
and the only other
comorbidity was hypertension,
you might want to try
lifestyle recommendations first
and then go on.
If we're going to tell a
hypercholesterolemia patient
to do lifestyle modifications,
what modifications are we talking about?
The same exercise,
but it's a little bit
different than the DASH diet
when we're talking about cholesterol.
Low fat?
Okay, very good.
Yeah, that's going to be the main focus.
You want to go over what
foods have fats in them.
A lot of people don't
think about the cheese
and the fried foods.
Maybe some of the healthier fats even,
like in cheese, they don't realize.
You want to make sure that
you talk about those with them
and then the same thing,
exercise, lowering alcohol content.
Alcohol's tricky because
it can actually increase
HDL slightly,
but that's still not
something we want to recommend
to our patient.
Just in general, same
lifestyle modifications.
I'll let you read through this.
Now we have a 48 year old male.
Dyslipidemia, hypertension, obesity, DVT.
Doctor wants to initiate Welchol,
which is a bile acid sequestrant.
LDL is high, 160 so it might
be time to add something else
if we can't titrate the atorvastatin.
Triglycerides, 320.
HDL, 42.
Total cholesterol, 199.
Would you guys initiate
Welchol at this time?
Let's say we can't
titrate the atorvastatin.
Yes?
- (mumbling) Most the class.
Nothing.
Okay, so Welchol actually you want to get
baseline lipids because
you can't initiate it
with triglycerides over 300.
So that's why that's important.
For the most part, you're not going to use
a bile acid sequestrant in the treatment
of dyslipidemia in general.
Statins are going to be our first line.
After that we can add on Zetia.
We can add on the new PCSK9 inhibitors,
which I'll talk about in a minute.
Niacin, fish oil, and then I would say
very last line would be
a bile acid sequestrant.
Yes?
Say it one more time, sorry?
Besides the statin?
Fish oil probably.
I mean, dyslipidemia is kind
of easy because it's statins
for the most part.
Welchol can be used and I have used it
in patients that are,
can't tolerate statins,
can't afford Zetia,
then you can use something like this.
It does have LDL benefit.
It's hard to take
and then you can't use it
if triglycerides are high
so it's a more difficult drug to use
but it's kind of there for an option
if all your other options are not,
if you're not able to
use your other options.
So again, don't want to use the face line.
Trigylcerides are over 300.
Discontinue if they get over 400,
because we don't want them to be over 500
and then have to treat
that with another drug.
And the most common one is, well,
Cholestyramine as well, but
Welchol or Cholestyramine
are going to be the most
common ones you see.
Lab values, you guys
already told me these.
It sounds like you know them very well,
so these are just here for you.
Less than 200, and these come
from our ATP3 guidelines.
I think, especially your
class might be the class
that's going to be the
most confused because
they came out with guidelines
while you were in school
and nobody knows how to use them.
Like, providers don't
know how to use them.
Physicians don't know how to use them
because the new guidelines don't even have
cholesterol goals in them.
So what most practitioners
are doing is merging
the ATP3 guidlelines, or the goals,
with the new guidelines, so there's still,
the other guidelines just basically say,
"Start a moderate
intensity statin," the end.
Like, there's no need to reach a goal.
But most practitioners are using these and
I would assume that the
NAPLEX is what they'll test
you on as well and you know those.
And if Capstone tests
you, it'll be on this.
Okay, so in general,
clinical ISDVD patients
need to be initiated on statins.
Patients with an LDL over 190
and that's just with no comorbidities,
if they have diabetes and are 40 to 75,
with an LDL between 70 to 189,
they need to be started,
so basically over 70,
70 to 189, and then the
rest captures the 190.
Also 40 to 75 with an
LDL between 70 to 189
and the 10 year ASCVD risk over 7.5.
So that's when you would start a statin.
Of course, contraindicate in
pregnancy like we talked about.
Anybody with active liver
disease, you're not going
to want to start a statin.
And if they have history of
liver disease, I'd be cautious
to start a statin if
there's another option
that you can use.
If you are going to start
one, that's when it would be
clinically indicated to
check the AST and ALT
more frequently when
you pull a lipid panel
and I do have patients
that have liver disease
that are on statins that do fine on them.
It's just I do check their LFTs.
Lipid panel, again, four to
12 weeks after initiation,
then every three to 12 months.
Usually once they're at
goal on a statin and they're
kind of good, I'll just
bump them to once a year
and make sure that it's
still good once a year.
So high intensity, we have Atorvastatin,
40 to 80, and then the
Crestor, moderate intensity
Simvastatin, 20 to 40,
80 we don't use any more.
And then Atorvastatin,
10 to 20 and low dose
Rosuvastatin and then low intensity,
where there's actually,
there's other ones,
Pravastatin, 80 milligrams is moderate
intensity as well.
Low intensity, there's no real
indication per the guidelines
for low intensity statins.
They either recommend
high intensity or moderate
intensity.
Clinically you might see Pravastatin
or Lovastatin because
they're the cheapest.
They're the cheapest and then Pravastatin,
if there's going to be interactions,
that's the best one to go to.
So you could do Pravastatin,
40 to 80 milligrams as well.
Main side effects, of
course the myopathy's
and myalgia's, elevated
liver enzymes and rabdo,
and we talked about all those things.
So what to do if they're
having myopathy's,
if they're having Rhabdomyolysis.
Hopefully no one has
any questions on that.
Next the fibric acid derivatives, again,
Gemfibrozil has that
interaction with statins,
particularly Simvastatin.
You want to make sure to try
and avoid that if possible.
And Fenofibrate's also another option.
It's a more expensive option,
though, if cost is an issue.
And then you want to make sure that you
same monitoring parameters,
monitor lipid panels.
So I talked a little bit about this,
but I want to talk some more about it,
just so that everybody's clear.
So Zetia is usually an add-on
therapy after you've kind of
maxed out statins or if the
patient cannot tolerate statins.
So statin plus Zetia or Zetia
if they can't tolerate statins
at all.
It has shown benefit, so it
does have a place in therapy.
It's just kind of an add-on
therapy after we've tried that.
PCSK9 inhibitors, did your
class have this in IT?
Or update? Okay.
So pretty new class of drugs,
the monoclonic antibodies.
There's four of them now.
There might have only been
two when you had it in IT,
but there's four now.
I couldn't even tell you
all the names off the top
of my head because they're
new and I don't use them
in practice.
Praluent, they have weird names,
but these are for the
homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia.
That's what they're FDA indicated for.
They also have an indication
if they're on the maximum
statin dose, you can add
one of these on as well.
They're very expensive
agents at this point.
I don't think many
practitioners are utilizing them
frequently unless they have that familial
hypercholesterolemia, but
it is an option and it is
FDA approved, so you should
know about those drugs
and then niacin I think
we covered pretty well
but again, it's going to increase the HDL,
lower the triglycerides.
Aim-High trial said
there's no real benefit.
Other studies kind of differ with that.
It's not in the guidelines
but you might see it used,
so if you do see it used, you
want to think about the liver
function test and the flushing,
so red flushing.
If they do have that, you can
give aspirin or ibuprofen,
30 to 60 minutes ahead of time.
Okay, any questions on that?
So let's take like really
just a five minute break
because there's not much
of the lecture left.
That being said, let's
talk about obesity briefly.
So obesity's very
straightforward, very simple,
but just a refresher on some of the drugs,
when you should use them, et cetera.
So I'll let you read
through that real quick.
So we have a 31 year old male, 194 pounds,
five foot five, doesn't
exercise, eats a lot of fast food
because he's in pharmacy school.
He's noticed some weight
around his abdomen
over the last few months, smokes, drinks.
So, calculate a BMI for him.
Hopefully you guys
remember how to do this.
Does anybody have one?
31.4, anyone get anything different?
I don't know if I, okay.
I have 29, but I could have
typed something in wrong.
So let's go with 29.
So this is just a refresher.
Underweight's going to be less than 18.5.
Normal is 18.5 to 24.9.
Overweight's 25 to 29.9.
Obese starts at 30,
technically, to 34.9 and
then they classify severely
obese as a separate thing,
35 to 39.9 and then anything over 40
is going to be morbidly
obese, and that's when
bariatric surgery can
be considered and we'll
go through that in just a minute.
So let's say their BMI's 29.
That's going to put him as overweight.
So what would you start at this point?
I heard a diet and exercise
and that's accurate.
So pharmacotherapy is not
indicated until their BMI's
over 30 and I'd like to
say that the guidelines,
I think sometimes students get confused.
It's not if you're BMI's over
30 you automatically start
on a pharmacotherapy agent.
Pharmacotherapy agents
for obesity are only going
to decrease you by about
three to six kilograms,
which is approximately
more or less five to 10%
of body weight.
Those should only be
initiated after trying diet
and exercise lifestyle
changes for about six months
with no improvement seen
and then the BMI's over 30
and they have comorbidities,
then you can start
a pharmacotherapy agent,
but it's not something
if you're reading a patient
case or if when you're out
on rotations you see a
patient has a BMI over 30,
we're going to put everybody
in the world on Orlistat
or something like that.
If that was the case,
most people in America
would be walking around on
some type of anti-obesity
medicine, right?
So that's just not the case.
So I want to make sure that that's clear,
that when you do see your Capstone cases,
you're not trying to start
people on that right away.
First line's always, always going to be
lifestyle recommendations.
So, smoking cessation counseling.
Again, exercising at least three
times a week for 30 minutes
ideally five times a week for 30 minutes,
sometimes it's hard to
get patients to start off
exercising five times a
week, 30 minutes a day.
So it's okay to stay,
"Let's start two days a week
"or three days a week" and
then increase from there.
Also that 30 minutes can
be broken up into 10 minute
increments.
They did a study with that,
so if you want to exercise
10 minutes before work,
10 minutes at lunch,
and then 10 minutes after
work, that's you're 30 minutes.
Technically.
So healthy diet, more or
less 1500 kilocals per day.
Three meals per day with two
snacks is the healthiest way
to eat and again, watching your calories,
watching your carbohydrates.
Increase raw foods, fruits
and vegetables are going
to be the healthiest.
The same things that we
talked about with the TLC diet
and the dash diet.
Same principles apply to obesity.
And then increase protein
and decrease fats and
carbohydrates.
So now read through that real quick.
So now he comes back and his BMI's higher.
So now it's 33, which is over
30, like we talked about.
His waist circumference is 42.
Do you know what the cutoff
is we're looking for men
for waist circumference?
40, mm-hmm, so he's over that.
Not eating healthy, not exercising,
and now he has hypertension
and dyslipidemia,
so we have some comorbidities.
What's an appropriate
treatment option at this point?
BELVIQ, okay.
So we could start a pharmacotherapy agent.
Other complications, this should
be pretty straightforward.
I mean, we could have
diabetes, heart issues,
brain issues, kidney issues, liver issues,
a lot of things come along with obesity.
And is bariatric surgery
an option at this point?
No.
Only over 40 and that still
has to be heavily considered
if they have a lot of
comorbidities, high cardiovascular
risk, and then it's a complicated process.
They have to decrease the
amount of food they eat
ahead of time and afterwards,
so really that's reserved
for very
- The last line, um, patients.
So there's a few different options.
The Orlistat, so Alli if
it's over the counter,
Xenical, um, Belviq is an option.
And then I just put some of the,
um, the ADR's here.
So headache, dizziness,
potential hypoglycemia.
Qsymia is a newer medicine,
so the Phentermine and Topiramate.
Um, and same type of symptoms,
dizziness, headache, insomnia.
And then we want to talk about
healthy diet and exercise, as we said.
Other complications...
Oh I forgot to mention
arthritis is a huge one.
I actually had a patient in
this morning before I came here,
she was 419 pounds, and
was just complaining
that all her joints hurt,
and she's on Diclofenac,
and she's tried all these NSAIDS,
and when it comes down to it,
I mean, she's having arthritic
pain from being 420 pounds,
so, um, really that's gonna
be your first time option,
is to lose the weight.
Sleep apnea, so people
with large neck radiuses.
Depression goes hand in hand, usually.
And no to the bariatric surgery.
So let's say this patient
was a 31 year old female,
would there be any weight loss medications
you would not want to give her?
The same thing with our Statins, right?
What are we thinking about
with a 31 year old female?
Pregnancy, yep.
OK, we lost that one.
Um, Belviq you shouldn't use, sorry.
I don't know where that slide went.
Um, in pregnant patients.
So again, it depends on the BMI,
but pregnant patients, if...
If the obesity is not a severe
extreme, immediate issue,
I would just do lifestyle modification,
and then worry about pharmacotherapy
after the baby, after they've
lost some of the baby weight.
If they're pregnant.
OK, so this patient was started on Belviq,
10 milligrams twice a day,
he's been eating healthy and exercising,
and he's kind of concerned that
he hasn't lost a lot of weight.
So he's lost some, 194 to 188.
What would you recommend?
OK, so 150 minutes a week exercise,
that's one point.
What about the medicine?
Would you keep him on
the same medicine, no?
I have one no.
Would you switch the medicine?
One yes.
OK, um, so after three months,
you want to reevaluate about
five percent of the body weight
you can initiate a different
agent at that point.
If that's still a route
you want to pursue.
Um, if they've kind of come down,
their BMI's down less than 30,
you might just want to try,
trial DC-ing it altogether.
So some general recommendations
from the guidelines,
they are very straightforward.
Um, calculate the BMI,
you know, you're worried
about risk for CVD,
diabetes, um, measuring
waist circumference.
Three to five percent of weight loss
results in clinically
meaningful reductions
in a lot of things, so your sugars,
your triglycerides, your blood pressure,
and it really does.
I've seen patients just lose,
you know, 10 to 20 pounds,
and all of a sudden their blood
pressure is under control,
sugars are under control.
It's amazing, watching it happen.
Um, weight loss diet,
so for women about 1200 to 1500,
for men 1500 to 1800.
Stupid men, get extra calories.
Um... (laughs)
That's my own thought,
not in the guidelines.
Um, let's see.
OK, and again, um,
bariatric surgery is only for BMI over 40,
or over 35 with comoribid conditions,
who haven't responded to pharmacotherapy
or other treatment options.
And then...
I just made this chart so you can see, um,
the main dosage and side effects.
You guys can read through that.
But I did want to show
you, I liked one slide.
So, some conditions that
you might want to consider
starting different
obesity medications with.
So CVD or uncontrolled, hypertension, um,
you might want to lean more towards
the Lorcaserin or Orlistat.
Depression, possibly
maybe lean more towards
the Bupropion and Naltrexone,
because of that Bupropion agent.
Um, migrane, possibly
Phentermine Topiramate
because of the Topiramate component.
Seizure, if the patient
has a history of seizures,
you might want to make sure that
you avoid the Bupropion
just like you would
smoking cessation, or depression.
And possible first choice,
Phentermine or Topiramate,
again from that Topiramate component.
So, if you just kind of are clueless,
and the patient has one
of these other conditions,
you could consider starting
one of these agents,
because of that.
Yes?
Do smoking cessation with this product?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, if you're using it...
Yes, if you're using it
for the obesity first,
and you also want them to
have smoking cessation,
you definitely can use that product,
because it has that Bupropion
in it, yes, good point.
Does anyone have any questions on obesity?
It's really stratightforward, but...
Hypertension questions,
dyslipidemia questions?
OK, hopefully that was helpful.
Have a good day, guys.