- That's the first thing you wanna do
before you add a third agent in this case.
Because he's already on lisinopril 40.
So from 40 to 80 you're not gonna see
too much of a clinical change.
So 40's kinda max therapeutic dose.
Amlodipine we can go all the way up to 10,
and he was only on 2.5,
and his blood pressure wasn't that high
that we were worried about
any hypertensive urgency
or emergency.
So that's a perfectly fine answer.
And then if he comes back
and it's still elevated,
I would titrate again.
So once he was on amlodapine 10
and lisinopril 40, and
it was still elevated,
what would you guys do?
So we'll go back to him.
I think I heard thiazide diuretic.
Yeah, okay, and that's right.
So you always wanna go back and think
what the guidelines say are
gonna be our first line agent.
And he's already on an ACE,
so it's ACE or ARB,
you don't want somebody
on an ACE and an ARB.
So he's already on that ACE,
already on the calcium channel blocker,
then you would just do a
thiazide-like diuretic.
And you can HCTZ, or chlorthalidone.
They're both proven. Yes, sir.
Yeah, I don't know why that's on there.
I don't know why the
calcium level's on there.
Don't worry about that for this case,
but yeah, you would wanna look at that.
Okay, so now this same patient
is having swelling in his legs,
and you examine him,
and he is having +1
pitting peripheral edema.
So why do you think that would be?
Okay, so Barclay thinks it's from
the calcium channel blocker, and I agree.
And you may see that
when you initiate a
calcium channel blocker,
or when you increase dose with
a calcium channel blocker.
What main side effects are we
worried about besides cough
with ACE inhibitors?
Edema, yep.
So, same thing, just in the lips usually.
Lips, tongue, face.
What about a main side effect
with our thiazide-like diuretics?
We kinda talked about that.
Hypercalcemia, and then the hypokalemia.
So really, electrolytes we wanna monitor.
And then what other side effects
do we wanna counsel on
with the thiazide-like diuretics?
Urination, okay.
So yeah, you always wanna tell them
to take it in the morning,
you may have increased urinary frequency.
So now we have a 50-year-old male
who has hypertension.
He has a past medical history of MI.
So what medication would somebody
that has had a past medical history of MI
need to be on?
A beta blocker.
So I think sometimes people
get confused with that too.
No, beta blockers are not
first line for hypertension
per JNC 8 guidelines.
But if you have a patient
that's had heart failure
or previous MI,
you're going to want them
to be on a beta blocker.
And that beta blocker
will serve two purposes.
It will help them with
their other problem,
and it will lower their blood pressure.
So that's a good thing.
So that's the one time that
the rule doesn't apply,
that it's not first line for hypertension.
Now the physician has decided,
okay they're on a beta blocker,
and they're on an ACE inhibitor,
I wanna add a diuretic.
And we know the sodium's
141, so that's fine,
potassium's 3.7, fine.
Creatinine clearance is
just a little bit low, 47.4.
So what diuretic would you think to add?
Chlorthalidone, okay.
That's a fine choice.
So if you look at the diuretics,
you don't wanna use HCTZ
when they get below 30,
but our patient's above 30 right now.
What other diuretics
are options in general
in hypertension, or for
treatment of other things?
What diuretics do we have?
Okay, so we have loop
diuretics, so furosemide.
I just wanna make it clear that usually
you're not going to use
furosemide to treat hypertension,
as the treatment of hypertension.
So they'll be put on it
for peripheral edema,
potentially from heart failure,
and then they might be on it PRN.
It will help with
lowering of blood pressure
if they're on it for something else,
but you wanna make sure
that you understand
that you don't put them on
it as a first line agent
for hypertension.
What else? What other diuretics?
Okay, potassium-sparing,
so we have spironolactone and eplerenone.
When would you use
those with hypertension?
Okay, so if they've had heart failure
it's a good option.
Also if they're resistant hypertension.
So if they're kind of on everything
that's first line already,
sometimes they're gonna have elevated ADH,
so aldosterone, and that's
a good option for them.
What are we worried about with
those potassium-sparing diuretics?
Okay, so potassium too
high, that's a good point.
So you always wanna make sure
you check their potassium
before you start them,
and then about a month
after you start them.
Same thing with ACEs and ARBs,
but this is even more so.
And what about main side effects?
Gynecomastia, yep.
Eplerenone has less gynecomastia
than spirinolactone.
So if your patient's
insurance is gonna cover it,
usually that's a little
bit better of an option.
Again, not first line in hypertension,
but if it's treatment
resistant, you can use it.
There's also triamterene you might see,
not first line,
but especially some of the
more old school doctors
will put them on triamterene, HCTZ.
And then I put this question in,
is MJ adequately beta blocked?
So let's take a look at the pulse here,
what do you guys think?
How do you tell if somebody's
adequately beta blocked?
Okay, I'm hearing 60-80 normal limits.
Any other guesses?
Usually about 60 to 70
is gonna mean that they're kind of
maximally adequately beta blocked.
60 to 80, I would agree with as well
if it's kind of on the
lower end of normal,
all the way down to 60.
Anything below 60
you're gonna kinda start
to worry a little bit,
but that's how you tell.
So if a patient, even if they're on
maximum dose atenolol,
maximum dose metoprolol,
if their pulse is still over 90
that means that beta blocker
is not adequately
working for that patient.
So you always wanna take
a look at that as well.
Okay, these I just put for your benefit,
I'm not reading through these.
Basically goal is gonna
be less than 140/90
as we've stated,
for the most part, for most diseases.
And then you have to go to
the individual guidelines
for each disease state.
So CKD guidelines for CKD,
which is actually now in
conjunction with the 140/90.
But it used to be different.
Diabetes used to be different,
now they're all kinda
getting on board together,
so that's good.
Then I just put in some basic slides,
I'm not redoing your IT slides,
you guys have already
had hypertension and IT.
But main medications used,
main side effects,
so our ACEs and our ARBs,
of course we wanna look out for cough,
and then elevated potassium.
And the edema like we talked about.
Calcium channel blockers,
when would you use a non-dihydropyridine
calcium channel blocker for hypertension?
Or would you use the non-dihydropyridine?
Not too sure?
Maybe some people are
sure, but I can't hear you.
The main difference is gonna be
that these act centrally, right,
they're gonna act on the heart.
So if it's an afib patient
that's trying to be rate-controlled,
hopefully you guys know,
I think you guys had
an afib case last week,
that these are gonna be your
calcium channel blockers
that you're going to.
If your patient also has hypertension,
that's when you would use that medication.
And then your dihyrdopyridines
are gonna act more peripherally
to vasodilate, and then reduce
your blood pressure that way.
So these are gonna be
when we're talking about
first line hypertension medicines,
and we say calcium channel blockers,
these are the medicines
that we're talking about.
Not so much these unless there's another
comorphic condition that indicates
that you would use
verapamil and diltiazem.
Beta blockers, again,
you wanna make sure
that your patient has another indication.
It wouldn't be your first choice to start
unless they're having
repeatedly high pulse
for unknown reason.
And in that case you
would definitely wanna
go ahead an get an EKG
to make sure something
else isn't going on.
But previous MI, or CHF,
that's when you would use these,
and you want to make
sure that you start low
and go slow.
That's how I learned beta blockers.
So start at a low dose and then titrate.
And same thing when you
discontinue beta blockers.
So you don't just wanna
stop a beta blocker,
you wanna decrease the dose
and titrate back down until
you stop the beta blocker.
Then once you have titrated down,
then you can start your new agent
if the purpose of titrating
is that you're switching agents.
You also wanna make sure,
because a lot of our hypertension patients
may also have diabetes,
so if they are on a beta blocker
it's important to tell them that
it might mask the signs and symptoms
of hypoglycemia.
All of them besides, what?
What won't a beta blocker mask?
Sweating.
So it'll mask the palpitations,
dizziness feeling,
but they'll still have the sweating
if they have the sweating.
Okay, that kind of does that.
So any major questions on hypertension?
I tried to kinda cover
through different cases.
Nope, okay.
Well, hopefully that helps to distinguish
a little bit in your head.
So now let's go on to dyslipidemia.
Let you guys read through that.
So we have a 45-year-old
Caucasian male who has type 2 diabetes.
And blood pressure's 135/86,
so just a little bit elevated.
Total cholesterol is 210.
What's our goal here?
200.
HDL is 37. What's our goal for men?
Over 40. And women?
50.
LDL is 170. What's our goal here?
100, so he's a diabetic patient.
And then it's controversial,
but the guidelines actually say
cardiovascular issues as well,
you can push to less than 70.
Triglycerides are 320,
what's our goal here?
Less than 150.
At what point do we worry
about triglycerides?
500, good.
Man, you guys are good today.
And A1C's just a little bit high at 7.2.
Overweight, 210 at 5'6.
Smokes two packs a day,
and somebody calculated their
ASCVD 10 year risk score
at 8.5%.
So what medicine would you want to start?
High-intensity statin, okay.
And which statins are those?
Atorvastatin, rosuvastatin, yep.
Lipitor and Crestor, okay.
And certain doses, so Crestor either dose,
but then atorvastatin is
gonna be the 40 to 80.
20 is actually a moderate intensity.
There we go.
So you wanna look at the age, 40 to 75,
diabetes, ASCVD risk,
and then you'll start a statin.
What labs do you wanna get
when you start a statin?
I heard CPK. What else?
I heard ALT. Let's go with both.
Liver function test, so AST, ALT.
And then you would ideally have
a lipid panel as well.
But CPK, and then your LFTs.
Now, you only monitor your CPK, LFTs
when clinically indicated.
So if your patient is having
signs or symptoms, or issues.
It's not something you're gonna get
every time you get a lipid panel.
So now this patient's
a 35-year-old female.
Would your choice of therapy be different,
and if yes, what would it be?