- The last line, um, patients.
So there's a few different options.
The Orlistat, so Alli if
it's over the counter,
Xenical, um, Belviq is an option.
And then I just put some of the,
um, the ADR's here.
So headache, dizziness,
potential hypoglycemia.
Qsymia is a newer medicine,
so the Phentermine and Topiramate.
Um, and same type of symptoms,
dizziness, headache, insomnia.
And then we want to talk about
healthy diet and exercise, as we said.
Other complications...
Oh I forgot to mention
arthritis is a huge one.
I actually had a patient in
this morning before I came here,
she was 419 pounds, and
was just complaining
that all her joints hurt,
and she's on Diclofenac,
and she's tried all these NSAIDS,
and when it comes down to it,
I mean, she's having arthritic
pain from being 420 pounds,
so, um, really that's gonna
be your first time option,
is to lose the weight.
Sleep apnea, so people
with large neck radiuses.
Depression goes hand in hand, usually.
And no to the bariatric surgery.
So let's say this patient
was a 31 year old female,
would there be any weight loss medications
you would not want to give her?
The same thing with our Statins, right?
What are we thinking about
with a 31 year old female?
Pregnancy, yep.
OK, we lost that one.
Um, Belviq you shouldn't use, sorry.
I don't know where that slide went.
Um, in pregnant patients.
So again, it depends on the BMI,
but pregnant patients, if...
If the obesity is not a severe
extreme, immediate issue,
I would just do lifestyle modification,
and then worry about pharmacotherapy
after the baby, after they've
lost some of the baby weight.
If they're pregnant.
OK, so this patient was started on Belviq,
10 milligrams twice a day,
he's been eating healthy and exercising,
and he's kind of concerned that
he hasn't lost a lot of weight.
So he's lost some, 194 to 188.
What would you recommend?
OK, so 150 minutes a week exercise,
that's one point.
What about the medicine?
Would you keep him on
the same medicine, no?
I have one no.
Would you switch the medicine?
One yes.
OK, um, so after three months,
you want to reevaluate about
five percent of the body weight
you can initiate a different
agent at that point.
If that's still a route
you want to pursue.
Um, if they've kind of come down,
their BMI's down less than 30,
you might just want to try,
trial DC-ing it altogether.
So some general recommendations
from the guidelines,
they are very straightforward.
Um, calculate the BMI,
you know, you're worried
about risk for CVD,
diabetes, um, measuring
waist circumference.
Three to five percent of weight loss
results in clinically
meaningful reductions
in a lot of things, so your sugars,
your triglycerides, your blood pressure,
and it really does.
I've seen patients just lose,
you know, 10 to 20 pounds,
and all of a sudden their blood
pressure is under control,
sugars are under control.
It's amazing, watching it happen.
Um, weight loss diet,
so for women about 1200 to 1500,
for men 1500 to 1800.
Stupid men, get extra calories.
Um... (laughs)
That's my own thought,
not in the guidelines.
Um, let's see.
OK, and again, um,
bariatric surgery is only for BMI over 40,
or over 35 with comoribid conditions,
who haven't responded to pharmacotherapy
or other treatment options.
And then...
I just made this chart so you can see, um,
the main dosage and side effects.
You guys can read through that.
But I did want to show
you, I liked one slide.
So, some conditions that
you might want to consider
starting different
obesity medications with.
So CVD or uncontrolled, hypertension, um,
you might want to lean more towards
the Lorcaserin or Orlistat.
Depression, possibly
maybe lean more towards
the Bupropion and Naltrexone,
because of that Bupropion agent.
Um, migrane, possibly
Phentermine Topiramate
because of the Topiramate component.
Seizure, if the patient
has a history of seizures,
you might want to make sure that
you avoid the Bupropion
just like you would
smoking cessation, or depression.
And possible first choice,
Phentermine or Topiramate,
again from that Topiramate component.
So, if you just kind of are clueless,
and the patient has one
of these other conditions,
you could consider starting
one of these agents,
because of that.
Yes?
Do smoking cessation with this product?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, if you're using it...
Yes, if you're using it
for the obesity first,
and you also want them to
have smoking cessation,
you definitely can use that product,
because it has that Bupropion
in it, yes, good point.
Does anyone have any questions on obesity?
It's really stratightforward, but...
Hypertension questions,
dyslipidemia questions?
OK, hopefully that was helpful.
Have a good day, guys.